Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 24: Intrapartum Assessment.
Electronic Fetal Monitoring Other Intrapartum Assessment Techniques Nonreassuring Fetal Status Meconium In The Amnionic Fluid Current Recommendations Intrapartum Surveillance Of Uterine Activity References Electronic fetal monitoring eclipsed periodic fetoscopic auscultation of the fetal heartbeat in the late 1960s .
It was hoped that the continuous graph-paper portrayal of the fetal heart rate (FHR), termed cardiotocography, would reflect pathophysiological events affecting the fetus.
Initially, electronic FHR monitoring was used primarily in complicated pregnancies.
Now, more than 85 percent of all live births in the United States undergo electronic FHR monitoring .
Electronic Fetal Monitoring.
# Internal (Direct) Electronic Monitoring.
Direct FHR measurement is accomplished by attaching a bipolar spiral electrode directly to the fetus .
The wire electrode penetrates the fetal scalp, and the second pole is a metal wing on the electrode.
The P wave, QRS complex, and T wave of the electrical fetal cardiac signal are amplified and fed into a cardiotachometer for heart rate calculation.
The peak R-wave voltage is the most reliably detected portion of the fetal electrocardiogram (ECG).
Time (t) in milliseconds between fetal R waves is fed into a cardiotachometer, and a new FHR is set with the arrival of each new R wave .
The phenomenon of continuous R-to-R wave FHR computation was known as beat-to-beat variability, and is now called baseline variability.
If present, fetal premature atrial contractions (PACs) cause the cardiotachometer to rapidly and erratically seek new heart rates and create the “spiking” shown Figure 24-3.
Figure 24-1.
With internal electronic fetal monitoring a bipolar electrode is attached to the fetal scalp for detection of fetal QRS complexes (F).
At times, the maternal heart and its electrical complex (M) also may be detected.
Figure 24-2.
Fetal electrocardiographic signals from the scalp electrode are used to compute continuous beat-to-beat heart rate.
Time intervals (t1, t2, t3) in milliseconds between successive fetal R waves are used by a cardiotachometer to compute instantaneous fetal heart rate.
In this example, the t2 interval has complexes that are close together, which indicates a slighted higher heart rate.
This is reflected in the vertical rise on the cardiotachometer graph.
ECG = electrocardiogram; PAC = premature atrial contraction.
Figure 24-3.
Standard fetal monitor tracing of heart rate using a fetal scalp electrode.
Spiking of the fetal rate reflects premature atrial contractions.
Electrical cardiac complexes detected by the fetal electrode include those generated by the mother.
However, the amplitude of the maternal ECG signal is diminished when recorded through the fetal scalp electrode.
Thus, maternal cardiac signals do not appear on the FHR tracing.
However, if the fetus is dead, maternal R waves can be still detected by the scalp electrode as the next best signal and are counted by the cardiotachometer .
Figure 24-4.
Placental abruption.
The fetal scalp electrode first detects the dying fetus’ heart rate.
After fetal death, the maternal electrocardiogram complex is detected and recorded.
# External (Indirect) Electronic Monitoring.
Although it avoids membrane rupture, external monitoring does not provide the precision of internal FHR monitoring .
Moreover, in some women, external monitoring may be difficult.
For example, fetuses of obese women have a greater amount of unmonitored time compared with those of normal-weight women .
With external monitoring, the FHR is detected through the maternal abdominal wall using the ultrasound Doppler principle .
The instrument contains a transducer that emits ultrasound and a sensor to detect a shift in frequency of the reflected sound.
The transducer is placed on the maternal abdomen at a site where fetal heart action is best detected.
A coupling gel must be applied because air conducts ultrasound waves poorly.
The device is held in position by an elastic belt.
Ultrasound
Doppler signals are edited electronically before FHR data appear.
Reflected ultrasound signals from moving fetal heart valves are analyzed through a microprocessor that compares incoming signals with the most recent previous signal.
This process, called autocorrelation, is based on the premise that the FHR has regularity, whereas “noise” is random and lacks regularity.
Several fetal heart motions must be deemed electronically acceptable by the microprocessor before the FHR is revealed.
Such electronic editing has greatly improved tracing quality.
Many fetal monitors are capable of interfacing with archival storage systems, which obviates maintaining actual paper tracings.
Other features of current external monitors include the ability to monitor twin fetuses, concurrently assess maternal heart rate, display fetal ECG, and record maternal pulse oximetry values.
Wireless, abdominal, dermal-patch, external array systems may improve the interpretability of intrapartum FHR tracings in obese women (Lempersz, 2020; Monson, 2020).
Wireless monitors use electrocardiography to accurately measure maternal and fetal heart rates yet allow patient mobility during labor.
# Fetal Heart Rate Patterns.
The interpretation of FHR patterns can be problematic without definitions and nomenclature.
In one study, three Maternal-Fetal Medicine specialists independently interpreted FHR tracings.
Agreement was poor for the most ominous tracings and was moderate for less severe patterns .
To help standardize definitions, the National Institute of Child Health and Human Development (NICHD) convened a working group .
The resulting definitions are used in this chapter and have been adopted by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019a).
Interobserver agreement improves when these standardized definitions are implemented .
Table 24-1.
Electronic Fetal Monitoring Definitions Pattern interpretation derives from the FHR that is portrayed on the monitor or graph paper.
Thus, the choice of vertical and horizontal scaling greatly affects patterns.
NICHD Workshop scaling parameters recommend that each centimeter on the vertical axis represents 30 beats per minute (bpm).
Measurement markers on this axis range from 30 to 240 bpm.
Along the horizontal axis, the chart recorder moves at a speed of 3 cm/min.
The time between each bold vertical line on this axis is 1 minute (see Fig. 24-4).
FHR patterns during labor are dynamic and can interchange rapidly.
Although intrapartum evaluation of fetal heart tracings occur every 5 to 30 minutes, tracing interpretation should reflect a longitudinal assessment beyond the current 5- to 30-minute segment (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2019b; Robinson, 2008; Vintzileos, 2016).
Thus, a full description should include an evaluation of changes or trends over time .
# Baseline Fetal Heart Activity.
This refers to FHR baseline characteristics apart from periodic accelerations or decelerations.
Elements include rate, variability, and distinct FHR patterns such as sinusoidal or saltatory.
Rate Beginning at 16 weeks’ gestation, the heart rate drops approximately 1 bpm each week (Pillai, 1990; Serra 2009).
This continues postnatally such that the average rate is 85 bpm by age 8 years .
This normal gradual slowing of the FHR is thought to correspond to maturation of parasympathetic (vagal) heart control .
The baseline FHR is the approximate mean rate during a 10-minute tracing segment and is rounded to increments of 5 bpm.
In any 10-minute window, the minimum interpretable baseline duration must be at least 2 minutes—otherwise the baseline is considered indeterminate.
For an indeterminate baseline, the previous 10-minute interval is used to determine the baseline heart rate.
If the baseline FHR is <110 bpm, it is termed bradycardia.
If the baseline rate is >160 bpm, it is called tachycardia.
The average FHR is considered the result of tonic balance between accelerator and decelerator influences on cardiac pacemaker cells.
In this concept, the sympathetic system is the accelerator
influence.
The parasympathetic system is the decelerator factor and mediated by vagal slowing of heart rate .
Heart rate also is under the control of arterial chemoreceptors such that both hypoxia and hypercapnia can modulate rate.
Prolonged hypoxia that is associated with a rising blood lactate level and severe metabolic acidemia induces an extended drop in heart rate .
Bradycardia.
In the third trimester, the normal mean baseline FHR ranges between 110 and 160 bpm.
But, pragmatically, a rate between 100 and 119 bpm, in the absence of other FHR changes, usually is not representative of fetal compromise.
Such mild bradycardias were observed in 2 percent of monitored pregnancies and averaged approximately 50 minutes in duration .
These low baseline heart rates have also been attributed to head compression from occiput posterior or transverse positions, particularly during second-stage labor.
However, fetal bradycardia may stem from congenital heart block or from fetal hypoxia due to maternal or fetal causes (Bravo-Valenzuela, 2018; Lepercq, 2021).
For example, Figure 24-4 shows bradycardia in a fetus dying from placental abruption.
Less often, sustained maternal hypothermia also can cause fetal bradycardia, but these uniquely involved fetuses apparently are not harmed by several hours of such bradycardia .
Tachycardia.
This is defined as a baseline FHR >160 bpm.
The most common explanation is maternal fever.
In some cases, fetal tachycardia may precede overt maternal fever .
Fetal tachycardia caused by maternal infection typically is not associated with fetal compromise unless it is associated with fetal sepsis or with significant FHR decelerations.
Other causes of fetal tachycardia include fetal compromise, cardiac arrhythmias, and maternal administration of parasympathetic inhibiting (atropine) or sympathomimetic (terbutaline) drugs.
Prompt treatment of the compromising event, such as alleviation of maternal fever or volume resuscitation, can result in fetal recovery.
The key feature to distinguish fetal compromise in association with tachycardia seems to be concomitant FHR decelerations .
Baseline Variability This is an important index of cardiovascular function and reflects a sympathetic and parasympathetic “push and pull” mediated by the fetal sinoatrial node.
This produces beat-to-beat fluctuations of the baseline FHR .
Variability describes these changes during 1 minute, which modify the baseline’s waviness .
Interpretation of variability is subjective and judges this waviness.
The NICHD workshop defined baseline variability as irregular fluctuations in the baseline excluding accelerations and decelerations .
They recommended the criteria shown in Figure 24-5.
for quantification of variability.
Normal variability shows oscillations that change 6 to 25 bpm.
FHR variability increases with advancing gestational age (Serra, 2009; Shuffrey, 2019).
Figure 24-5.
Baseline fetal heart rate variability shown in the following five panels.
1. Undetectable, absent variability.
2. Minimal variability, ≤5 bpm.
3. Moderate (normal) variability, 6 to 25 bpm.
4. Marked variability, >25 bpm.
5. Sinusoidal pattern.
This differs from variability in that it has a smooth, sinelike pattern of regular fluctuation and is excluded in the definition of fetal heart rate variability.
Increased Variability.
Several physiological and pathological processes affect variability.
Greater variability accompanies fetal breathing and body movements (Dawes, 1981; Zizzo, 2020).
Shuffrey and colleagues (2020) showed the FHR had enhanced variation in state 4F (active awake state) compared with 1F (quiet state) and 2F (active state) .
However, in one study of 390 fetuses, greater intrapartum variability was associated with abnormal fetal arterial cord blood gas measurements but without increased neonatal morbidity rates .
Decreased Variability.
Absent variability and minimal variability are defined as no baseline fluctuation or changes ≤5 bpm.
These are shown in Figure 24-5.
panels 1 and 2.
Of greatest concern, diminished variability can
be an ominous sign that indicates a seriously compromised fetus.
According to Esplin (2020), metabolic acidemia depresses the fetal brainstem or heart to create the loss of variability.
Thus, diminished variability, when it reflects fetal compromise, likely reflects acidemia rather than hypoxia.
Severe maternal acidemia also can lower fetal variability, for example, in a mother with diabetic ketoacidosis.
Reduced baseline FHR variability is the single most reliable sign of fetal compromise.
Moderate variability is associated with a normal umbilical cord pH in 98 percent of cases .
Absent or minimal variability is associated with fetal acidemia, but it predicts an umbilical cord pH <7.15 in only 12 to 31 percent of cases (Parer, 2006; Williams, 2003).
In a study of 2200 consecutive deliveries, authors concluded that variability by itself could not be used as the only indicator of fetal well-being .
Comorbid fetal tachycardia or FHR decelerations also may help predict fetal acidemia (Esplin, 2020; Vintzileos, 2016).
Another common cause of diminished variability is administration of some analgesic drugs during labor .
These can depress the central nervous system and include narcotics, barbiturates, phenothiazines, tranquilizers, and general anesthetics.
As one specific example, variability regularly diminishes within 5 to 10 minutes following intravenous (IV) meperidine administration, and the effects may last 60 minutes or longer (Hill, 2003; Petrie, 1993).
IV butorphanol has similar effects .
And, chronically administered buprenorphine suppresses FHR and movement .
Corticosteroids also decrease fetal movement and thereby dampen variability .
Magnesium sulfate can diminish variability and is widely used in the United States for fetal neuroprotection, tocolysis, and seizure prophylaxis in preeclampsia.
In a study of nearly 250 term gestations, its administration led to decreased variability but without evidence of adverse neonatal effects .
Others echo these findings (Nensi, 2014; Verdurmen, 2017).
In sum, variability is affected by fetal physiology, and its meaning differs depending on clinical setting.
A decrease in variability but without decelerations is unlikely to reflect fetal hypoxia .
A persistently flat FHR baseline—absent variability—within the normal baseline rate range and without decelerations may reflect a prior fetal insult that has resulted in neurological damage .
Cardiac Arrhythmia When fetal cardiac arrhythmias are first suspected using electronic monitoring, findings can include baseline bradycardia, tachycardia, or most commonly in our experience, abrupt baseline spiking (see Fig. 24-3).
An arrhythmia can only be documented, practically speaking, when scalp electrodes are used.
Some fetal monitors can be adapted to output the scalp electrode signals into an ECG recorder.
Because only a single lead is obtained, analysis and interpretation of rhythm and rate disturbances are severely limited.
In one study, rate and rhythm disturbances in 934 normal pregnancies were evaluated between 30 and 40 weeks’ gestation.
Arrhythmias, episodes of bradycardia 180 bpm were encountered in 3 percent .
Most supraventricular arrhythmias carry little significance during labor unless fetal heart failure, as evidenced by hydrops, is coexistent.
Many supraventricular arrhythmias disappear in the immediate neonatal period, although some are associated with structural cardiac defects .
Intermittent baseline bradycardia is frequently due to congenital heart block.
Conduction defects, most often complete atrioventricular (AV) block, usually are found in association with maternal connective tissue diseases .
Antepartum evaluation of the fetus with an identified arrhythmia and treatment options are discussed in Chapter 19 (p. 368).
Most fetal arrhythmias without comorbid fetal hydrops are inconsequential during labor, but they may hinder interpretation of FHR tracings and thereby necessitate cesarean delivery.
Sonographic evaluation of fetal anatomy and echocardiography can be useful.
Generally, without evidence of fetal hydrops, neonatal outcome is not measurably improved by pregnancy intervention.
At Parkland Hospital, intrapartum fetal cardiac arrhythmias, especially those associated with clear amnionic fluid, are typically managed conservatively.
Sinusoidal Heart Rate A sinusoidal baseline is one with a sine wave–like undulating pattern with a frequency of 3 to 5 cycles per minute for at least 20 minutes.
A true sinusoidal pattern such as that shown in panel 5 of Figure 24-5 can be observed with fetal intracranial hemorrhage, severe fetal asphyxia, or severe fetal anemia.
The last may stem from alloimmunization, fetomaternal hemorrhage, twin-twin transfusion syndrome, fetal parvoviral infection, or vasa previa with bleeding.
The pathophysiology of sinusoidal patterns is unclear, in part due to varying definitions.
One group proposed that the pattern relates to fetal arterial blood pressure and oscillations in the baroreceptor-chemoreceptor feedback mechanism .
Modanlou (1982, 2004) proposed adoption of a strict definition for true sinusoidal FHR that is most likely ominous.
This criteria eliminates the influence of maternal medications.
1. Stable baseline FHR of 120 to 160 bpm with regular oscillations 2.
Amplitude of 5 to 15 bpm (rarely greater) 3.
2 to 5 cycles per minute 4.
Absent variability and accelerations 5.
Oscillation of the sinusoidal waveform above or below a baseline 6.
No concurrent drugs such as narcotics Other investigators classify sinusoidal heart rate patterns into mild— amplitude 5 to 15 bpm; intermediate—16 to 24 bpm; and major—≥25 bpm.
Increasing amplitude correlates with advancing fetal risk (Murphy, 1991; Neesham, 1993).
Importantly, insignificant sinusoidal patterns have been reported following administration of meperidine, morphine, alphaprodine, and butorphanol (Angel, 1984; Egley, 1991; Epstein, 1982).
When due to narcotics, this pattern has a sine frequency of 6 cycles per minute.
A sinusoidal pattern also has been described with chorioamnionitis, fetal distress, and umbilical cord occlusion .
Investigators have concluded that intrapartum sinusoidal fetal heart patterns are not generally associated with fetal compromise (Johnson, 1981; Young, 1980a).
Thus, management is usually dictated by the clinical setting.
Pseudosinusoidal describes intrapartum sine wave–like baseline variation coupled with periods of acceleration.
In one study, this pattern was seen in 15 percent of monitored labors .
Mild pseudosinusoidal patterns were associated with use of meperidine and epidural analgesia.
Intermediate pseudosinusoidal patterns were linked to fetal sucking or transient episodes of fetal hypoxia caused by umbilical cord compression.
In another study, 4 percent of fetuses demonstrated sinusoidal patterns transiently during normal labor .
These authors noted patterns lasting for 90 minutes in some cases.
# Periodic Fetal Heart Rate Changes.
These refer to visually apparent deviations from baseline.
Acceleration refers to a rise in FHR above the baseline, and deceleration is a drop below the baseline rate.
For the latter, terms used in the United States are early, late, or variable and refer to the temporal relationship between the deceleration and contractions.
Waveform shapes also aid pattern recognition and are described subsequently.
The NICHD Workshop (2008) considered decelerations to be recurrent if they accompanied ≥50 percent of contractions in any 20-minute period.
Accelerations These are an abrupt FHR increase above the baseline and are defined by the onset-to-peak rise within 30 seconds .
At ≥32 weeks’ gestation, an acceleration is one that peaks at a point ≥15 bpm above baseline.
Its duration is ≥15 seconds but <2 minutes from onset to baseline return .
Before 32 weeks, a peak ≥10 bpm and duration lasting 10 seconds to 2 minutes is considered normal.
Prolonged acceleration is one lasting ≥2 minutes but <10 minutes.
Accelerations occur antepartum and intrapartum.
Proposed mechanisms for intrapartum accelerations include fetal
movement, stimulation by uterine contractions, umbilical cord occlusion, fetal scalp stimulation, scalp blood sampling, and acoustic stimulation.
Accelerations are common during labor.
These are virtually always reassuring and almost always confirm that the fetus is not acidemic at that moment .
Accelerations reflect intact neurohormonal cardiovascular control mechanisms linked to fetal behavioral states.
In one analysis of FHR tracings in nearly 2000 fetuses, 99.8 percent showed sporadic accelerations during labor.
FHR accelerations during the first or last 30 minutes of labor were a favorable sign for fetal well-being .
Their absence during labor, however, is not necessarily an unfavorable sign unless coincidental with other nonreassuring changes.
The chance of acidemia in the fetus that fails to respond to stimulation despite an otherwise nonreassuring pattern approximates 50 percent (Clark, 1984; Smith, 1986).
Early Deceleration This physiological response shows a gradual FHR decline and then return to baseline that mirrors the contraction .
Etiologically, head compression and dural stimulation probably cause vagal nerve activation, which mediates the FHR deceleration .
Freeman and associates (2003) defined early decelerations as those generally seen in active labor between 4 and 7 cm cervical dilation.
In their definition, the degree of deceleration is generally proportional to the contraction strength and rarely falls below 100 to 110 bpm or 20 to 30 bpm below baseline.
These decelerations are common during active labor and not associated with tachycardia, loss of variability, or other FHR changes.
Early decelerations are considered benign and not associated with fetal hypoxia, acidemia, or low Apgar scores.
Figure 24-6.
An early fetal heart rate deceleration characteristically shows a gradual decline and recovery in the heart rate that coincide with the onset and recovery of the contraction.
The nadir of the deceleration is ≥30 seconds after the deceleration onset.
Late Deceleration This deceleration is a smooth, gradual, symmetrical decline in the FHR that begins at or after the contraction peak and returns to baseline only after the contraction has ended.
It reaches its nadir within 30 seconds of its onset .
Typically, a late deceleration’s depth is <10 to 20 bpm below baseline.
These usually are not accompanied by accelerations.
Figure 24-7.
A late fetal heart rate deceleration characteristically shows a gradual decline in the heart rate that starts at or after the contraction’s peak and recovers after the end of the contraction.
The deceleration nadir occurs ≥30 seconds after the deceleration’s onset.
Late decelerations often reflect poor uterine perfusion or placental dysfunction.
In one animal study, uteroplacental perfusion was intentionally compromised, and the lag between contraction onset and late deceleration onset was directly related to basal fetal oxygenation .
The lower the fetal PO2 before contractions, the shorter the lag to the late deceleration’s onset.
This lag reflects the time necessary for the fetal PO2 to fall below a critical level necessary to stimulate arterial chemoreceptors, which mediate the decelerations.
Late decelerations are the first FHR consequence of uteroplacentalinduced hypoxia.
Fetal acidemia develops after frequent or prolonged periods of hypoxia.
However, late decelerations alone do not predict fetal acidemia .
Instead, late decelerations plus decreased variability, which itself is an indicator of less activity in the cardioregulatory center of the medulla, are more predictive of fetal acidemia and neonatal morbidity (Cahill, 2018; Holzmann, 2015).
Cahill and coworkers (2018) calculated the total area within the below-baseline curves of decelerations.
They found that increasing area was more predictive of fetal acidemia than other FHR characteristics.
Generally, any process that produces maternal hypotension, excessive uterine activity, or placental dysfunction can induce late decelerations.
The two most common are hypotension from epidural analgesia and
uterine hyperactivity from oxytocin stimulation.
Maternal hypertension, diabetes, and collagen vascular disorders can cause chronic placental dysfunction.
Placental abruption can acutely produce late decelerations.
Variable Deceleration This is the most frequent deceleration pattern encountered during labor and is attributed to umbilical cord occlusion.
In a study of more than 7000 tracings, variable decelerations were identified in 40 percent when labor had progressed to 5 cm dilation and in 83 percent by the end of first-stage labor .
The slope of FHR change is abrupt and erratic, giving the waveform its jagged shape .
A variable deceleration is defined as a drop in the FHR that begins with the contraction’s onset and reaches a nadir in <30 seconds.
The deceleration lasts between 15 seconds and 2 minutes, and its depth is ≥15 bpm in amplitude.
The onset of deceleration typically varies with successive contractions.
Figure 24-8.
A variable fetal heart rate deceleration characteristically shows an abrupt drop in the heart rate, and its onset commonly varies with successive contractions.
The deceleration depth measures ≥15 bpm, lasts ≥15 seconds, and has an onset-to-nadir phase <30 seconds.
Its total duration is <2 minutes.
Etiologically, variable deceleration often reflects some degree of umbilical cord occlusion.
In one animal study, Hon (1959) assessed the effects of umbilical cord compression on FHR.
He found lengthening and deepening of the deceleration curve with longer occlusion times.
In another study, variable decelerations in fetal lambs occurred only after umbilical blood flow was reduced by at least 50 percent .
Two patterns of variable decelerations are shown in Figure 24-9.
The deceleration denoted by “A” is very much like that seen with complete umbilical cord occlusion in experimental animals.
However, deceleration “B” differs and displays an acceleration before and after the deceleration component.
Lee and coworkers (1975) proposed that this form was caused by differing degrees of cord occlusion.
In this scheme, occlusion of only the vein reduces fetal blood return and thereby triggers a baroreceptor-mediated acceleration.
With increasing intrauterine pressure and subsequent complete cord occlusion, fetal systemic hypertension develops due to obstructed umbilical artery flow.
This stimulates a baroreceptor-mediated deceleration.
Presumably, the aftercoming acceleration represents the same events occurring in reverse .
Ball and Parer (1992) concluded that variable decelerations are mediated vagally and that the vagal response may be due to chemoreceptor or baroreceptor activity or both.
Partial or complete cord occlusion produces an increase in afterload (baroreceptor) and a drop in fetal arterial oxygen content (chemoreceptor).
Both result in vagal activity leading to deceleration.
Figure 24-9.
Variable fetal heart rate decelerations.
Deceleration (B) exhibits “shoulders” of acceleration compared with deceleration (A).
Figure 24-10.
Schematic representation of the fetal heart rate effects with partial and complete umbilical cord occlusion.
Uterine pressures generated early in a contraction cause cord compression predominantly of the thin-walled umbilical vein.
The resulting decrease in fetal cardiac output leads to an initial compensatory rise in fetal heart rate.
As cord compression intensifies, umbilical arteries are then also compressed.
The resulting rise in fetal systolic blood pressure leads to a vagal-mediated fetal heart rate deceleration.
As the contraction abates and compression is relieved first on the umbilical arteries, elevated fetal systolic blood pressures drop and the deceleration resolves.
A final increase in fetal heart rate is seen as a result of persistent umbilical vein occlusion.
With completion of the uterine contraction and cord compression, the fetal heart rate returns to baseline.
BP = blood pressure.
Thus, variable decelerations represent FHR reflexes that reflect either blood pressure changes due to interruption of umbilical flow or changes in
oxygenation.
It is likely that most fetuses have experienced brief but recurrent periods of hypoxia due to umbilical cord compression during gestation.
The great dilemma for the obstetrician in managing variable FHR decelerations is determining when variable decelerations are pathological.
According to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019a), recurrent variable decelerations with minimal to moderate variability are indeterminate, whereas those with absent variability are abnormal.
A saltatory FHR baseline is another pattern linked to umbilical cord complications during labor .
The pattern is rapidly recurring couplets of acceleration and deceleration causing relatively large oscillations of the FHR baseline.
We also observed a relationship between cord occlusion and the saltatory pattern in postterm pregnancies .
In the absence of other FHR findings, this pattern does not signal fetal compromise.
Figure 24-11.
Saltatory baseline fetal heart rate showing rapidly recurring couplets of acceleration combined with deceleration.
Prolonged Deceleration This pattern is defined as an isolated deceleration with a depth >15 bpm and length ≥2 minutes but <10 minutes from onset to return to baseline .
Prolonged decelerations are difficult to interpret because they are seen in many different clinical situations.
Frequent causes are cervical examination, uterine hyperactivity, cord entanglement, and maternal supine hypotension.
Epidural, spinal, or paracervical analgesia may induce a prolonged deceleration .
Of women given epidural analgesia during labor in one analysis at Parkland Hospital, prolonged deceleration was noted in 1 percent .
Other causes include placental abruption, umbilical cord knots or prolapse, maternal hypoperfusion or hypoxia from any cause, maternal seizures, fetal scalp-electrode application, impending birth, or maternal Valsalva maneuver.
Figure 24-12.
Prolonged fetal heart rate deceleration due to uterine hyperactivity.
Approximately 3 minutes of the tracing are shown, but the fetal heart rate returned to normal after uterine hypertonus resolved.
Vaginal delivery later ensued.
The placenta can effectively resuscitate the fetus if the original insult does not recur immediately.
Occasionally, such self-limited prolonged decelerations are followed by loss of variability, baseline tachycardia, and even a period of late decelerations.
These all resolve as the fetus recovers.
Freeman and colleagues (2003) emphasize that the fetus may die during prolonged decelerations.
Thus, management of prolonged decelerations can be extremely tenuous.
Management of isolated prolonged decelerations is based on bedside clinical judgment, which inevitably will sometimes be imperfect given the unpredictability of these decelerations.
# Fetal Heart Rate Patterns During Second-stage Labor.
Decelerations are virtually ubiquitous during the second-stage labor.
In one study, only 1.4 percent of more than 7000 deliveries lacked decelerations during this stage .
Both cord and fetal head compressions are implicated as causes of decelerations and of baseline bradycardia in this stage.
In one series, profound, prolonged FHR deceleration in the 10 minutes preceding vaginal delivery was associated with intervention and good fetal outcomes .
In a later extension of this series, similarly prolonged second-stage decelerations were also associated with a stillbirth and neonatal death .
These experiences attest to the unpredictability of the FHR during second-stage labor.
In the analysis noted earlier by Cahill and associates (2018), an increasing total deceleration area found in the final 120 minutes prior to delivery was most predictive of fetal acidemia.
A combination of deceleration area plus a 10-minute period of tachycardia was most predictive of neonatal morbidity.
Others have reported similar findings (Krebs, 1981; Picquard, 1988).
Gull and colleagues (1996) observed that abrupt FHR decelerations to <100 bpm associated with lost variability for ≥4 minutes predicted fetal acidemia.
Thus, second-stage
decelerations plus an abnormal FHR baseline (bradycardia or tachycardia and/or absent variability) are associated with greater risk for fetal compromise .
Figure 24-13.
Cord-compression fetal heart rate decelerations in second-stage labor associated with tachycardia and loss of variability.
The umbilical cord arterial pH was 6.9.
# Computerized Interpretation.
FHR pattern interpretations are subjective.
Thus, the potential for computer assistance to enhance the precision of identifying abnormal patterns appeared promising.
The INFANT Collaborative Group (2017) studied whether the addition of computer-based decision-support software for FHR pattern interpretation lowered the number of poor neonatal outcomes.
In this large trial, women were randomly assigned to computer-assisted interpretation or to conventional clinical interpretation.
Rates of adverse perinatal outcomes that included intrapartum stillbirth, early neonatal death, and neonatal encephalopathy were not improved, and a subset showed no difference in neurological development at 2 years.
Cesarean delivery rates were similar in both groups.
In a subsequent analysis of 71 adverse outcomes, computer interpretation of FHR tracings was deemed completely valid in only 34 percent of cases.
Computer analysis missed a significant portion of decelerations, reduced variability, and tachysystole .
Other Intrapartum Assessment Techniques.
# Fetal Scalp Blood Sampling.
According to the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019a), measurements of the pH in capillary scalp blood may help identify the fetus in serious distress.
However, this group also emphasizes that neither normal nor abnormal scalp pH results accurately predict neonatal outcome.
Although used in other countries, the procedure is not available at most hospitals in the United States.
With sampling, an illuminated endoscope is inserted through the dilated cervix after membrane rupture and is pressed firmly against the fetal scalp.
The skin is wiped clean with a cotton swab and coated with a silicone gel, which allows fetal blood to accumulate as discrete globules.
An incision is made through the fetal scalp to a depth of 2 mm with a special blade on a long handle.
As a drop of blood forms on the surface, it is immediately collected into a heparinized glass capillary tube.
The blood pH is measured promptly.
The pH of fetal capillary scalp blood is usually lower than that of umbilical venous blood and approaches that of umbilical arterial blood.
In one algorithm, if the pH is ≥7.25, labor is observed, and if between 7.20 and 7.25, the pH measurement is repeated within 30 minutes .
If the pH is <7.20, another scalp blood sample is collected immediately, and delivery is performed promptly if the low pH level is confirmed.
Otherwise, labor is allowed to continue, and scalp blood samples are repeated periodically.
The only benefits reported for scalp blood pH testing are fewer cesarean deliveries for fetal distress .
However, Goodwin and coworkers (1994) showed a decrease in the scalp pH sampling rate from approximately 1.8 percent in the mid-1980s to 0.03 percent by 1992.
This drop in sampling rate was not associated with a higher cesarean delivery rate for fetal distress.
They concluded that scalp blood pH sampling was unnecessary.
Kruger and colleagues (1999) have assessed fetal scalp blood lactate concentration as an adjunct to pH.
In one large randomized study, fetuses received scalp blood pH analysis or scalp blood lactate analysis .
The authors found either to be equivalent in predicting fetal acidemia.
In a secondary analysis, prediction of low Apgar scores or admission to the neonatal intensive care unit did not differ between lactate and pH groups .
However, cesarean delivery rates were higher in the lactate group.
# Scalp Stimulation.
Clark and coworkers (1984) have suggested that fetal scalp stimulation is an alternative to scalp blood sampling.
This proposal stemmed from the observation that FHR acceleration followed pinching the fetal scalp with an Allis clamp just before
obtaining scalp blood and was invariably associated with a normal pH level.
However, failure to provoke acceleration was not uniformly predictive of fetal acidemia.
In another study of 58 cases in which the FHR accelerated >10 bpm after 15 seconds of digital scalp stroking, 100 percent had a scalp blood pH >7.20 .
However, without an acceleration, only 30 percent had a scalp blood pH >7.20.
Authors of a recent prospective study concluded that scalp stimulation was a reliable alternative to fetal scalp blood pH determination .
In our practice, scalp stimulation is often one element of intrapartum assessment of the fetus with a category II tracing.
# Vibroacoustic Stimulation.
FHR acceleration in response to vibroacoustic stimulation is another substitute for fetal scalp blood sampling .
The technique uses an electronic artificial larynx placed 1 cm from or directly onto the maternal abdomen .
Response to vibroacoustic stimulation is considered normal if the FHR accelerates within 15 seconds after the stimulus and with prolonged fetal movements .
Lin and colleagues (2001) prospectively studied vibroacoustic stimulation in 113 women in labor with either moderate to severe variable or late FHR decelerations.
They concluded that this technique effectively predicts fetal acidosis in cases with variable decelerations.
In the setting of late decelerations, its prediction of fetal acidosis, however, is limited.
Other authors found vibroacoustic stimulation in second-stage labor did not predict neonatal outcome or enhance labor management .
Skupski and coworkers (2002) performed a metaanalysis of reports on intrapartum fetal stimulation tests.
These included fetal scalp puncture for blood pH testing, fetal scalp pinching, vibroacoustic stimulation, and digital stroking of the fetal scalp.
Results were similar for all four methods.
These authors concluded that intrapartum stimulation tests were useful to exclude fetal acidemia.
They cautioned, however, that these tests are “less than perfect.
# Fetal Pulse Oximetry.
Using technology similar to that of adult pulse oximetry, this tool measures fetal oxyhemoglobin saturation once membranes are ruptured.
A unique padlike sensor is inserted through the cervix and positioned against the fetal face.
Using fetal pulse oximetry, the lower limit for normal fetal oxygen saturation is generally considered to be 30 percent (Gorenberg, 2003; Stiller, 2002).
However, when measured in umbilical arterial blood, fetal oxygen saturation normally varies greatly.
In one large trial of this technology, women with term fetuses that developed abnormal FHR patterns were assigned to conventional FHR monitoring alone or FHR monitoring plus continuous fetal pulse oximetry .
The use of fetal pulse oximetry significantly reduced the cesarean delivery rate for nonreassuring fetal status from 10.2 to 4.5 percent.
No neonatal benefits or adverse effects were associated with fetal pulse oximetry.
Based on these observations, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approved marketing of the Nellcor N-400 Fetal Oxygen Monitoring System.
However, three subsequent trials compared fetal pulse oximetry with standard care.
In each, neonatal outcomes were similar between study arms.
In one, the addition of oximetry significantly reduced cesarean delivery rates for fetal indications .
However, two studies found no difference in cesarean delivery rates between the two study arms (Bloom, 2006; Klauser, 2005).
Because of these findings, in 2005, the manufacturer discontinued device sales in the United States.
# Fetal Electrocardiography.
As fetal hypoxia worsens, the fetal ECG changes.
Namely, the mature fetus with hypoxemia develops an elevated ST segment and a progressive rise in the T-wave height that can be expressed as a T:QRS ratio .
Increasing T:QRS ratios are thought to reflect fetal cardiac ability to adapt to hypoxia and appear before neurological damage.
Further worsening of hypoxia then leads to progressively negative ST-segment deflection that creates a biphasic form.
It is reasonable to
consider that STsegment abnormalities might occur late in the course of fetal compromise.
Indeed, it has been hypothesized that ST-segment changes reflect myocardial tissue hypoxia.
Figure 24-14.
A. Generation of T:QRS ratio from a normal ST segment.
B. ST-segment elevation in hypoxic conditions.
C. Biphasic ST-segment waveform with progressive fetal hypoxia.
Because of these findings, these parameters have been evaluated as an adjunct to conventional fetal monitoring.
The technique requires internal FHR monitoring and special equipment to process the fetal ECG.
In 2005, the manufacturer—Neoventa Medical—received FDA approval for their STsegment analysis program named the STAN system.
Several studies have evaluated ST-segment changes with fetal monitoring.
In one randomized trial of 2400 pregnancies, neonatal outcomes were not improved compared with those in which conventional FHR monitoring alone was used .
However, the cesarean delivery rate for fetal distress declined in those with ST-segment analysis.
Subsequent studies revealed conflicting data regarding lower rates of operative delivery, fetal acidemia, and neonatal encephalopathy (AmerWåhlin, 2001; Becker, 2012; Doria, 2007).
In a trial by the NICHD, 5532 women were randomly assigned to an STsegment analysis and 5576 to standard intrapartum management.
The primary outcome was a composite of one or more of seven events associated with fetal compromise .
In the ST-segment analysis group, clinician actions were directed by predetermined guidelines.
These stipulated that intervention should be withheld, that is, expectant management adopted, for at least 60 minutes despite the presence of minimal variability; variable decelerations lasting ≥60 seconds or dropping to a level ≥60 bpm; recurrent late decelerations; or prolonged decelerations lasting >2 minutes, so long as no ST-segment abnormality was present.
These guidelines did not pertain to the standard group.
Notably, in the ST-segment analysis group, 55 (20 percent) of the 287 cesarean deliveries performed for fetal indications were done even though trial guidelines indicated that labor could continue.
In these cases, physicians likely perceived the FHR patterns to reflect those formerly accepted in their usual practice as nonreassuring.
These results showed that STAN system had no effect on neonatal outcome or cesarean delivery rates .
A subsequent systematic review reached similar conclusions .
These results have essentially eliminated use of ST-segment analysis in the United States, but it is still used in Europe.
Nonreassuring Fetal Status.
The term fetal distress is too broad and vague to be applied with any precision to clinical situations .
Uncertainty regarding the diagnosis based on FHR pattern interpretation has given rise to descriptions such as reassuring or nonreassuring.
The former suggests confidence in the health of the fetus.
In contrast, a nonreassuring designation suggests inability to remove doubt.
However, these assessments are subjective judgments that are inevitably imperfect and must be recognized as such.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019d) recommends use of these terms followed by a description of the findings.
The difficulty in assigning a nonreassuring label to FHR patterns stems in part from the fact that these patterns reflect fetal physiology more so than pathology.
Heart rate control stems from interconnected mechanisms that depend on blood flow and oxygenation.
Moreover, these mechanisms are influenced by the preexisting state of fetal oxygenation.
Chronic placental insufficiency is one example.
Thus, normal labor is a process of repeated fetal hypoxic events and can infrequently lead to significant acidemia .
# Diagnosis.
Identification of nonreassuring fetal status based on FHR patterns is imprecise.
One study of interobserver agreement with FHR pattern interpretation found that consensus varied .
Specifically, experts agreed on 62 percent of normal patterns, 42 percent of suspicious patterns, and only 25 percent of pathological patterns.
In another study, 17 experts reviewed 50 tracings on two occasions, at least 1 month apart.
Approximately 20 percent changed their own interpretations, and approximately 25 percent did not agree with the interpretations of their colleagues .
In an attempt to resolve this imprecision, the NICHD recommended a three-tier system for FHR pattern classification .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) has recommended its use.
To assess this tiered system, Jackson and associates (2011) studied 48,444 women in labor and found that category I patterns were observed in 99.5 percent of tracings.
Category II patterns were found in 84.1 percent, and category III patterns were seen in 0.1 percent (54 women).
During labor, 84 percent of women had a mix of categories.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists and the American Academy of Pediatrics (2019d) has concluded that a category I or II tracing with a 5-minute Apgar score >7 or with normal arterial blood acid–base values is not consistent with an acute hypoxic-ischemic event.
Table 24-2.
Three-Tier Fetal Heart Rate Interpretation System Other studies have evaluated this three-tiered system.
In one, the incidence of umbilical cord acidemia (pH ≤7.10) was correlated retrospectively with FHR characteristics during the 30 minutes preceding delivery.
None of the three categories demonstrated a significant association with cord blood acidemia .
Sholapurkar (2012) has challenged the validity of the three-tier system because most abnormal FHR patterns fall into the indeterminate category II.
It was suggested that this resulted from most FHR decelerations being inappropriately classified as variable and attributed to cord compression.
Parer and King (2010) compared this situation in the United States with that of other countries in which a consensus on classification and management has been reached by their professional societies.
These authors note that the NICHD three-tier system is inadequate because category II contains a vast heterogenous mixture of patterns that prevents development of a management strategy.
Weissbach and associates (2018) found that duration of category II tracings does not predict perinatal asphyxia, but the individual components of diminished variability and fetal tachycardia are predictive.
Parer and Ikeda (2007) had previously proposed a color-coded five-tier system for both FHR interpretation and management.
Two subsequent reports have compared the five- and three-tier systems.
In one, the two systems were similar in FHR interpretations for tracings that were either very normal or very abnormal .
The other study found that the five-tier system had better sensitivity than the three-tier one .
It is apparent that despite decades of electronic FHR monitoring, a consensus on FHR pattern interpretation and diagnosis is still lacking .
# Meconium in the Amnionic Fluid.
Obstetricians have long realized that meconium during labor is an inaccurate predictor of fetal distress or asphyxia.
Indeed, although 12 to 22 percent of labors are complicated by meconium, only a few are linked to neonatal mortality.
In an investigation from Parkland Hospital, meconium was found to be a “low-risk” obstetrical hazard because the perinatal mortality rate attributable to meconium was only 1 death per 1000 live births .
Three etiological theories may explain the tenuous association between meconium passage and neonatal mortality.
First, fetuses may pass meconium in response to hypoxia, and meconium therefore signals fetal compromise .
Second, however, in utero passage of meconium may represent normal gastrointestinal tract maturation under neural control .
A final theory posits that common but transient umbilical cord entrapment leads to vagal stimulation, increased bowel peristalsis, and meconium passage .
Jovanovic and Nguyen (1989) observed that meconium aspirated into fetal lungs during gasping caused aspiration syndrome only in asphyxiated animals.
Ramin and associates (1996) studied almost 8000 pregnancies with meconium-stained
amnionic fluid delivered at Parkland Hospital.
Meconium aspiration syndrome was significantly associated with fetal acidemia at birth.
Further analysis of umbilical blood gases suggested that the fetal compromise associated with meconium aspiration syndrome was an acute event.
This is because most acidemic fetuses had abnormally elevated PCO2 values rather than a pure metabolic acidemia.
Other significant correlates of aspiration included cesarean delivery, forceps to expedite delivery, intrapartum FHR abnormalities, depressed Apgar scores, and need for assisted ventilation at delivery.
Ramin and colleagues (1996) hypothesized that the pathophysiology of meconium aspiration syndrome includes, but is not limited to, fetal hypercarbia, which stimulates fetal respiration leading to aspiration of meconium into the alveoli.
Lung parenchymal injury is secondary to acidemia-induced alveolar cell damage.
In this pathophysiological scenario, meconium in amnionic fluid is a fetal environmental hazard rather than a marker of preexisting compromise.
This proposed pathophysiological sequence is not all-inclusive, because it does not account for approximately half of the cases of meconium aspiration syndrome in which the fetus is not acidemic at birth.
Thus, the high incidence of meconium observed in the amnionic fluid during labor often represents normal physiological fetal passage of gastrointestinal contents.
Although normal, such meconium becomes an environmental hazard when fetal acidemia from hypercarbia supervenes.
Importantly, such acidemia occurs acutely, and therefore meconium aspiration is unpredictable and likely unpreventable.
Growing evidence indicates that many newborns with meconium aspiration syndrome have suffered chronic hypoxia before birth .
In one study, 60 percent of neonates diagnosed with meconium aspiration syndrome had umbilical artery blood pH ≥7.20, which implies that the syndrome was unrelated to the neonatal condition at delivery .
Similarly, comorbid markers of chronic hypoxia, such as elevated fetal erythropoietin levels and increased nucleated red blood cell counts in newborns, suggest that chronic hypoxia is involved in many meconium aspiration syndrome cases (Dollberg, 2001; Jazayeri, 2000).
Previously, routine obstetrical management of a newborn with meconiumstained amnionic fluid included intrapartum suctioning of the oropharynx and nasopharynx.
Current recommendations state that newborns with meconiumstained amnionic fluid, regardless of their vigor, should no longer routinely receive intrapartum suctioning (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2021; Wyckoff, 2015).
Suctioning is reserved for those with airway obstruction.
They also recommend that an appropriately credentialed team with full resuscitation skills be available .
# Management Options.
Initial management of variant FHR patterns aims to correct any fetal insult, if possible.
Suggestions are listed in Table 24-3.
The woman is moved to a lateral position, and supplemental oxygen is provided by mask.
Correcting maternal hypotension caused by regional analgesia and discontinuing oxytocin both serve to improve uteroplacental perfusion.
Vaginal examination excludes a prolapsed cord or impending delivery.
Simpson and James (2005) assessed the benefits of three maneuvers in 52 women with fetal oxygen saturation sensors already in place.
They provided IV hydration with 500 to 1000 mL of lactated Ringer solution given over 20 minutes; lateral versus supine positioning; and administration of supplemental oxygen at 10 L/min using a nonrebreathing mask.
Each of these maneuvers significantly raised fetal oxygen saturation levels.
A randomized trial comparing oxygen via face mask to room air showed no difference in resolution of recurrent decelerations (75 percent versus 86 percent), time to resolution of recurrent decelerations, and total deceleration area .
Table 24-3.
Some Resuscitative Measures for Category II or Category III Tracings Tocolysis Terbutaline sulfate given to relax the uterus can be a temporizing maneuver in the
management of nonreassuring FHR patterns during labor.
A single 250-μg IV or subcutaneous injection is used to inhibit uterine contractions and thereby improve fetal oxygenation.
One study described 368 pregnancies in which terbutaline was used to relieve contractions in preparation for cesarean delivery that was already planned for nonreassuring fetal status .
Compared with a group not receiving tocolysis, the treated group had fewer 5-minute Apgar scores <7.
Small IV doses of nitroglycerin —60 to 180 μg—also have reported benefit .
In one comparator study, both agents resolved tachysystole, but nitroglycerin lowered mean arterial blood pressures .
Two systematic reviews both noted that data were limited and reached differing views on tocolysis benefits (Bullens, 2015; Leathersich, 2018).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) cites that evidence is insufficient to recommend tocolysis for nonreassuring FHR patterns.
We consider terbutaline during labor stimulation to resolve tachysystole-associated prolonged decelerations.
However, the chance of success is balanced against terbutaline’s side effects should cesarean delivery be needed for unresolved bradycardia.
Namely, β agonist–related maternal tachycardia exacerbates the tachycardia associated with surgery itself.
We consider maternal cardiopulmonary disease, poorly controlled hyperthyroidism, and maternal or fetal tachycardia with loss of variability to be contraindications.
Amnioinfusion Early studies infused saline through an intrauterine pressure catheter in laboring women who had either variable or prolonged decelerations attributed to cord compression (Miyazaki, 1983, 1985).
Such therapy improved the FHR pattern and decreased cesarean delivery rates for fetal indications.
For variable decelerations, other studies also support amnioinfusion to reduce variable deceleration frequency, improve neonatal outcome, and lower cesarean delivery rates (Hofmeyr, 2012; Raghuraman, 2020a).
The American Academy of Pediatrics and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017) conclude that amnioinfusion is a reasonable approach to treat repetitive variable decelerations but not late decelerations.
As a prophylactic tool in known cases of oligohydramnios, evidence does not support amnioinfusion to prevent cord compressionrelated decelerations (Nageotte, 1991; Ogundipe, 1994).
Last, attempts to flush out or dilute thick meconium are not recommended (Fraser, 2005; Xu, 2007).
Despite differing amnioinfusion protocols, most provide a 500- to 800mL bolus of warmed normal saline, which is followed by a continuous infusion of 3 mL/min (Owen, 1990; Pressman, 1996).
Rinehart and colleagues (2000) administered a 500-mL bolus of normal saline at room temperature alone or this bolus plus a continuous infusion at 3 mL/min.
They included 65 women with variable decelerations and found neither method to be superior.
Potential amnioinfusion complications are summarized in Table 24-4 from a U.S. survey of fellowship and residency directors .
Table 24-4.
Complications Associated with Amnioinfusion from a Survey of 186 Obstetrical Units # Fetal Heart Rate Patterns and Brain Injury.
Studies attempting to correlate FHR patterns with brain injury have primarily examined infants identified in medicolegal actions.
Phelan and Ahn (1994) reported that among 48 fetuses later found to be neurologically impaired, a persistent nonreactive FHR tracing was already present at the time of admission in 70 percent.
They concluded that fetal neurological injury occurred predominantly before arrival to the hospital.
When they looked retrospectively at FHR patterns in 209 brain-injured newborns, they concluded that there was not a single unique pattern associated with fetal neurological injury .
Others have reported the same conclusion (Nakao, 2020; Phelan, 2000).
In a review of literature published between 1966 and 2006 on the effect of FHR monitoring to prevent perinatal brain injury, the summary found no benefit .
FHR patterns necessary for perinatal brain
damage have been studied in animals.
Myers (1972) described the effects of complete and partial asphyxia in rhesus monkeys .
Complete asphyxia was produced by total occlusion of umbilical blood flow that led to prolonged deceleration.
Fetal arterial pH did not drop to 7.0 until approximately 8 minutes after complete cessation of oxygenation and umbilical flow.
At least 10 minutes of such prolonged deceleration were required before surviving fetuses demonstrated brain damage.
Figure 24-15.
Prolonged deceleration in a rhesus monkey shown with blood pressure and biochemical changes during total occlusion of umbilical cord blood flow.
The most common FHR pattern during labor—due to umbilical cord occlusion—requires considerable time to significantly affect the fetus in experimental animals.
Clapp and colleagues (1988) partially occluded the umbilical cord for 1 minute every 3 minutes in fetal sheep.
Rocha and associates (2004) totally occluded the umbilical cord for 90 seconds every 30 minutes for 3 to 5 hours a day for 4 days without producing necrotic brain cell injury.
Results from such studies suggest that the effects of umbilical cord entrapment depend on the degree, the duration, and the frequency of such occlusions.
The contribution of intrapartum events to subsequent neurological handicaps has been greatly overestimated, as discussed in Chapter 33 (p. 601).
For brain damage, the fetus must be exposed to much more than a brief period of hypoxia.
Moreover, the hypoxia must cause profound, just barely sublethal metabolic acidemia.
Because of this, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019d) has recommended umbilical cord blood gases be obtained when cesarean delivery is performed for fetal compromise or when a low 5-minute Apgar score, severe fetal-growth restriction, an abnormal FHR tracing, or multifetal gestation is present .
Until recently, the prognosis for moderately affected newborns with hypoxic-ischemic encephalopathy (HIE) was poor.
More recently, studies show that brain cooling administered to newborns suffering neonatal HIE could ameliorate the development of subsequent cerebral palsy .
# Benefits of Electronic Fetal Heart Rate Monitoring.
Several false assumptions underlie the expectation of improved perinatal outcome with electronic FHR monitoring.
One is that nonreassuring fetal status is a slowly developing phenomenon and that electronic monitoring permits early detection of the compromised fetus.
Another presumption is that all fetal injury develops in the hospital.
In reality, most neurologically damaged fetuses suffer insults before arrival at labor units.
The very term fetal monitor implies that this inanimate technology in some fashion “monitors.
The assumption is made that if a dead or damaged fetus is delivered, the tracing strip must provide some clue, because this device was monitoring fetal condition.
These assumptions led to expectations that all neonatal deaths or injuries were preventable.
By the end of the 1970s, questions regarding the efficacy, safety, and costs of electronic monitoring were being voiced.
Banta and Thacker (2002) reviewed the benefits, or lack thereof, of electronic FHR monitoring.
More recently, a review of 13 randomized trials involving more than 37,000 women concluded that electronic FHR monitoring was associated with fewer neonatal seizures but a higher rate of cesarean and operative vaginal deliveries .
However, rates of perinatal mortality or cerebral palsy did not decline.
Grimes and Peipert (2010) concluded that such monitoring has failed as a public health screening program.
They noted that the positive-predictive value of electronic FHR monitoring for fetal death in labor or cerebral palsy is near zero and reflects that “almost every positive test result is wrong.
Epidemiologically, two large studies in the United States reported a decline in neonatal mortality rates due to electronic FHR monitoring.
However, the highest effect was seen in preterm neonates (Ananth, 2013; Chen, 2011).
Of note, caution must be used in
interpreting these studies, as epidemiological association does not establish causation .
At admission for labor, most women with low-risk pregnancies are monitored for a short time.
In one study, 3752 low-risk women in spontaneous labor were randomly assigned at admission to either FHR auscultation or 20 minutes of electronic FHR monitoring .
Electronic FHR monitoring did not improve neonatal outcome.
Moreover, its use resulted in a greater number of interventions, including operative delivery.
A similar study echoed these neonatal outcomes .
Last, admission FHR monitoring for low-risk pregnancy is associated with a higher cesarean delivery rate but not improved neonatal outcomes in one Cochrane review .
At Parkland Hospital in July 1982, an investigation began to ascertain whether all women during labor should undergo electronic monitoring .
In alternating months, universal electronic FHR monitoring was rotated with selective FHR monitoring, which was the prevailing practice.
During the 3-year investigation, more than 17,000 labors were managed using universal electronic FHR monitoring, and these outcomes were compared with a similar-sized cohort of women selectively monitored electronically.
No significant differences were found in any perinatal outcome.
With universal monitoring, a small but significant increase in the cesarean delivery rate for fetal distress was noted.
Thus, greater application of electronic FHR monitoring at Parkland Hospital did not improve perinatal results but did slightly raise the frequency of cesarean delivery for fetal distress.
More recently, a Cochrane Database review found that intermittent auscultation was associated with a higher cesarean delivery rate compared with continuous monitoring .
# Current Recommendations.
Methods most commonly used for intrapartum FHR monitoring include intermittent auscultation with a fetal stethoscope or a Doppler ultrasound device, or continuous electronic monitoring of FHR and uterine contractions.
Evidence has not identified the most effective method nor the frequency or duration of fetal surveillance that ensures optimum results.
That said, Table 24-5 summarizes current guidelines from the American Academy of Pediatrics and American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2017).
Intermittent auscultation or continuous electronic monitoring is considered an acceptable method of intrapartum surveillance in both low- and high-risk pregnancies.
The recommended interval between checking the heart rate, however, is longer in the uncomplicated pregnancy.
When auscultation is used, it is recommended that it be performed after a contraction and for 60 seconds.
It also is recommended that a 1-to-1 nurse–patient ratio be used if auscultation is employed.
The position taken by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) acknowledges that available data do not show a clear benefit to the use of electronic monitoring over intermittent auscultation.
At Parkland Hospital, all high-risk labors are continuously monitored electronically.
In low-risk pregnancies, both intermittent auscultation and continuous electronic monitoring are used depending on clinical circumstances, including the woman’s desire to ambulate.
Table 24-5.
Guidelines for Methods of Intrapartum Fetal Heart Rate Monitoring Intrapartum Surveillance Of Uterine.
Activity.
Analysis of electronically measured uterine activity permits some generalities concerning the relationship of certain contraction patterns and labor outcome.
However, uterine muscle efficiency to bring about delivery varies greatly.
Thus, caution should be exercised before diagnosing true labor or its absence solely from a monitor tracing.
With internal monitoring of contractions, amnionic fluid pressure is measured between and during contractions.
An intrauterine pressure catheter is placed into the uterus with its distal tip above the presenting part.
The catheter tip contains a pressure sensor and allows calculation of intrauterine pressure with each contraction .
With external monitoring, uterine
contractions can be measured by a displacement transducer in which the transducer button, or “plunger,” is held against the maternal abdominal wall.
As the uterus contracts, the button moves in proportion to the strength of the contraction.
This movement is converted into a measurable electrical signal that indicates the relative intensity of the contraction.
It has generally been accepted that internal monitoring provided a more accurate measure of intensity.
That said, in a randomized trial comparing internal versus external monitoring of uterine contractions in 1456 women, the two methods yielded equivalent operative delivery rates and neonatal outcomes .
Figure 24-16.
Placement of an intrauterine pressure catheter to monitor contractions and their pressures.
The catheter, contained within the light blue introducer, is inserted into the uterus and placed along one side of the fetal head.
The catheter is then gently advanced into the uterus, and the introducer is withdrawn.
# Patterns of Uterine Activity.
Caldeyro-Barcia and Poseiro (1960), from Montevideo, Uruguay, were pioneers in elucidating the patterns of spontaneous uterine activity throughout pregnancy.
Waves of uterine activity were usually measured using intraamnionic pressure catheters.
But early in their studies, as many as four simultaneous intramyometrial microballoons also were used to record uterine pressure.
Contraction intensity was defined as the rise in this pressure above a resting pressure baseline.
These investigators also introduced the concept of Montevideo units to define uterine activity .
With this definition, uterine performance is the product of contraction intensity in mm Hg multiplied by the number of contractions in a 10-minute span.
For example, three contractions in 10 minutes, each with 50-mm Hg intensity, would equal 150 Montevideo units.
According to Caldeyro-Barcia and Poseiro (1960), clinical labor usually commences when uterine activity reaches values between 80 and 120 Montevideo units.
This translates into approximately three contractions of 40 mm Hg every 10 minutes.
Importantly, no clear-cut division marks labor onset, which is a gradual and progressive transition.
In first-stage labor, uterine contractions progressively grow in intensity from approximately 25 mm Hg at labor commencement to 50 mm Hg at its end.
At the same time, the frequency advances from three to five contractions per 10 minutes, and uterine baseline tone rises from 8 to 12 mm Hg. Uterine activity is further enhanced during second-stage labor, aided by maternal pushing.
Contraction intensity of 80 to 100 mm Hg is typical, and the uterus contracts as frequently as five to six times each 10 minutes.
Hauth and coworkers (1986) quantified uterine contraction pressures in 109 women at term who received oxytocin for labor induction or augmentation.
Most of these women achieved 200 to 225 Montevideo units, and 40 percent had up to 300 units to effect delivery.
The authors suggested that these levels of uterine activity should be sought before consideration of cesarean delivery for presumed dystocia .
Interestingly, the duration of uterine contractions—60 to 80 seconds— does not lengthen appreciably from early active labor through the second stage (Bakker, 2007; Pontonnier, 1975).
Presumably, this duration constancy serves fetal respiratory gas exchange.
During a uterine contraction, as the intrauterine pressure exceeds that of the intervillous space, respiratory gas exchange is halted.
This leads to functional fetal “breath holding,” which has a 60- to 80-second limit that remains relatively constant.
Caldeyro-Barcia and Poseiro (1960) also observed empirically that uterine contractions are clinically palpable only after their intensity exceeds 10 mm Hg.
Moreover, until the intensity of contractions reaches 40 mm Hg, the uterine wall can readily be depressed by the finger.
At greater intensities, the uterine wall then becomes so hard that it resists easy depression.
Uterine contractions usually are not associated with pain until their strength
exceeds 15 mm Hg. Presumably, this is the minimum pressure required to distend the lower uterine segment and cervix.
Hendricks (1968) observed that “the clinician makes great demands upon the uterus.
The uterus is expected to remain well relaxed during pregnancy, to contract effectively but intermittently during labor, and then to remain in a state of almost constant contraction for several hours postpartum.
Figure 2417 demonstrates an example of normal uterine activity during labor.
Uterine activity progressively and gradually rises from early through late labor.
Interestingly, uterine contractions after birth are identical to those resulting in delivery of the newborn.
Logically, the uterus that performs poorly before delivery is also prone to atony and puerperal hemorrhage.
Figure 24-17.
Intrauterine pressure recorded through a single catheter.
A. Prelabor.
B. Early labor.
C. Active labor.
D. Late labor.
E. Spontaneous activity ½ hour postpartum.
F. Spontaneous activity 2½ hours postpartum.
Redrawn from Hendricks CH: Uterine contractility changes in the early puerperium.
Clin Obstet Gynecol 1968 Mar;11(1):125–144.
# Uterine Contraction Terminology.
Terms to describe uterine contractions have been recommended by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b).
Normal uterine activity is defined as five or fewer contractions in 10 minutes, averaged during a 30-minute span.
Tachysystole is more than five contractions in 10 minutes, averaged over 30 minutes.
Tachysystole can be applied to spontaneous or induced labor.
The term hyperstimulation was abandoned.
Stewart and associates (2012) prospectively studied uterine tachysystole in 584 women undergoing labor induction with misoprostol at Parkland Hospital.
A higher rate of adverse neonatal outcomes was not associated with an increasing number of contractions per 10 minutes or per 30 minutes.
Counts of six or more contractions in 10 minutes, however, were significantly associated with FHR decelerations.
# Electronic Fetal Monitoring Complications.
Electrodes for FHR evaluation and catheters for uterine contraction measurement are both associated with infrequent but potentially serious complications.
Rarely, an intrauterine pressure catheter may lacerate a fetal vessel in the placenta during placement.
Also with insertion, placental and possibly uterine perforation can cause hemorrhage, abruption, and spurious recordings that have resulted in inappropriate management.
Severe cord compression has been described from entanglement with the pressure catheter.
Injury to the fetal scalp or breech by a FHR electrode is rarely severe.
However, face presentations pose risk for eye or mouth trauma.
Both the fetus and the mother may be at greater risk of infection from internal monitoring .
Scalp wounds from the electrode may become infected, but subsequent cranial osteomyelitis is rare (Brook, 2005; Eggink, 2004; McGregor, 1989).
Certain maternal infections that include human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), herpes simplex virus, and hepatitis B and C virus are relative contraindications to internal FHR monitoring .